Guide to the Charles W. Hoyt Company Records, 1894-1973 and undated (bulk 1909-1928) RL.00218
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Charles W. Hoyt Company records
1894-1973 and undated (bulk 1909-1928)
1909-1928
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Charles W. Hoyt Company
RL.00218
4.4 Linear Feet
3,300 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Access to one scrapbook in the Charles W. Hoyt Papers is closed for preservation reasons; a photocopy is available for use. Two Nazi Medals may be used only with staff supervision. For further information, consult a reference archivist.
In addition, all or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Charles W. Hoyt Company Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1995. The records were donated by Tony Hoyt on behalf of the Hoyt family.
Biographical / Historical
Charles W. Hoyt
1862 Born
1889-1891 Traveling salesman throughout New England
1891-1894 Attended Yale University; graduated with a degree in mechanical engineering
1894-1899 Traveling salesman for his father's wholesale company
1899-1904 Secretary and treasurer of a large wholesale firm selling to grocery and general store trade
1903-1928 Ran a small mail order stationery business, the George B. Woolson Co., selling Woolson Economy Expense Books
1904 Became manager of the New Haven branch of Armour and Company
1904-1909 General superintendent of the Southern New England Division of Armour and Company
1909 Apr. Opened the Charles W. Hoyt Advertising Agency in New Haven, Conn.
1910 Hoyt Agency opened branch office in New York run by C.B. Donovan
1913 and 1918 Published Scientific Sales Management
1913 Traveled with wife Effie Smith Hoyt to Europe
1914 Hoyt Agency incorporated as Hoyt Service, Inc. Hoyt registered the phrase Planned Advertising and began to sell plans for $1000 Hoyt Family moved to Garden City, N.Y.
1916 June Became Charter member of the New York Sales Managers' Club
1923 Hoyt Service, Inc. changed its name to Charles W. Hoyt Company, Inc.
1924 July-Oct. Traveled with Effie, along with sons Winthrop and Everett Hoyt, to England for the International Meeting of the Advertising Clubs of the World
1928 Sept. 16 Killed in a riding accident Winthrop and Everett Red Hoyt took over the agency, with Winthrop as President and Everett as Secretary; Ralph Talley became Chairman of the Board
1963 Jan. 23 Effie Smith Hoyt died
Biographical / Historical
Winthrop Hoyt
1900 Dec. 2 Born to Charles W. and Effie Smith Hoyt in New Haven, Conn.
1918-1922 Attended Yale University, where he worked on the Yale News
1922-1924 Employed with the American Agriculturist
1924-1925 Employed with W.S. Crawford, Ltd., advertising agency, London, England
1925 Joined the Charles W. Hoyt Company, Inc.
1928 Took over the Hoyt Company as president following the death of Charles W. Hoyt
1942 Resigned as President of agency to serve in World War II as an intelligence officer with the US Army Air Force
1946 Rejoined the Charles W. Hoyt Company, Inc. and was elected Chairman of the Board
1949 Feb. 5 Married Lyn Chappel in Darien, Conn.
1953-1954 Served as Secretary-Treasurer of the American Association of Advertising Agencies
1989 Sept. 9 Died
Biographical / Historical
Everett
1905 Born to Charles W. and Effie Smith Hoyt in New Haven, Conn.
1923-1927 Attended Yale University; graduated with a BA
1927 Worked in the Springfield, Mass. office of the Charles W. Hoyt Company, Inc.
1928 Sept. 16 Became secretary of the Hoyt Company following the death of Charles W. Hoyt
1942 Named President of Charles W. Hoyt Company, Inc.
Biographical / Historical
The Charles W. Hoyt Company, Inc.
1909 Apr. The Charles W. Hoyt Advertising Agency opened in New Haven, Conn.
1910 Hoyt Agency opened branch office in New York run by C.B. Donovan
1914 Hoyt Agency headquarters moved from New Haven, Conn. to New York, N.Y. and agency incorporated as Hoyt Service, Inc. Hoyt registered the phrase Planned Advertising and began to sell plans for $1000
1923 Hoyt Service, Inc. changed its name to Charles W. Hoyt Company, Inc.
1928 Sept. 16 Following the death of Charles W. Hoyt, Winthrop and Everett Red Hoyt took over the agency, with Winthrop as President and Everett as Secretary; Ralph Talley became Chairman of the Board
1929 Agency discontinued selling plans and adopted a more conventional style of advertising
1965 Charles W. Hoyt Company, Inc. was sold to Rumrill Agency and became the Rumrill-Hoyt Agency. Later Rumrill-Hoyt was absorbed into the Saatchi and Saatchi and Rowland agency.
Collection Overview
The records of the Charles W. Hoyt Company advertising agency span the years 1894-1973 with the bulk dating between 1909-1928. The collection primarily documents the founding and operation of the company, and to a lesser extent the personal activities of the Hoyt family (Charles, Effie, Winthrop, and Everett) and Winthrop's service during World War II in the U. S. Army Air Force. Materials include correspondence, scrapbooks, company publications and manuals, financial records, clippings, diaries, writings, drawings, photographs, house advertisements, Nazi medals, song lyrics, and printed material. Very little information exists in the collection concerning the Hoyt Company's clients. The only client advertisements that survive were produced for Merck and Co. The Hoyt company scrapbooks document some activities for clients including Arnold Bakers, Golden Blossom Honey, Jamaica Tourist Board, KLM, Stanley Home Products, the Charles B. Woolson Co. and the State of New Hampshire. The collection contains correspondence between family members as well as between the company and Merck and Co., the Charles B. Knox Co., and William Benton, one of the founders of the Benton and Bowles advertising agency. Another notable person mentioned in the collection is Hoyt Company employee Samuel Meek, who would go on to become an important executive for the J. Walter Thompson Company advertising agency. The collection is organized into the Company Series; the Family Series; and the Winthrop Hoyt World War II Series. Large-format items are located in the Oversize Materials.
The Company Series contains the bulk of material in the collection and is concerned with the founding, and subsequent operation of the Charles W. Hoyt Company from 1909 to 1965 by Charles W. Hoyt (until his death in 1928), and then by his sons Winthrop and Everett Red Hoyt. The Company produced and sold advertising and marketing plans to clients in addition to providing other advertising services. Charles Hoyt's philosophy of planned advertising is well-documented.
The Family Series consists of personal diaries, correspondence, photographs and other printed materials relating to Hoyt family members as distinct from the activities of the Charles W. Hoyt Company. Family members for whom materials exist include Charles W. Hoyt, Effie Smith Hoyt, Winthrop Hoyt, and Everett Red Hoyt.
The Winthrop Hoyt World War II Records Series documents Hoyt's service during the war as an intelligence officer in the United States Army Air Force. It includes correspondence and writings, photographs, Nazi medals and other materials.
Oversize Materials include items removed from other series due to their size.
Clippings (information artifacts); Photographs; Scrapbooks; World War, 1939-1945 -- Military intelligence -- United States; Diaries; United States. Army air forces -- History -- World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945; Hoyt family; Advertising agencies -- United States; Advertising agencies; Advertising executives; Charles B. Woolson Company; Charles W. Hoyt Company; Hoyt, Charles W., 1862-1928; Hoyt, Effie Smith, ?-1963; Benton & Bowles; Hoyt, Everett Red, 1905-; Hoyt, Winthrop, 1900-1989; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Merck and Co; Charles B. Knox Co; Meek, Samuel W. (Samuel Williams), 1895-; Benton, William, 1900-1973
- Company Series, 1909-1967 and undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Documents the founding and operation of the Company and is divided into the following categories: Company Manuals, Correspondence, Financial Records, Photographs, Printed Materials, Scrapbooks, and Writings.
  - Company Manuals, 1912-1965
    Contains manuals written and compiled by Charles W. Hoyt and by his sons. They detail Charles's philosophy of advertising, describe the Hoyt Company's practices and standards of operation, and provide biographical information about employees and their responsibilities. The manuals are comprised of clippings, memoranda, printed materials, and writings of Charles W. Hoyt. Some contain biographical data on Charles, Winthrop, and Everett Hoyt, and other executives. Only two client plans survive in the collection -- one for Merck and Co. and the other for ABC Manufacturing Company. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1912-1917, 2 folders (Box 1)
      Report entitled Analysis of a Complete Advertising Campaign
    - 1924 June 15 (Box 1)
      Marketing and Advertising Plan for the ABC Manufacturing Company
    - 1925 (Box 1)
      The Laws of Successful Advertisement Writing, compiled by Charles W. Hoyt
    - 1925-1927 (Box 1)
      Standard Practice, Account Executive, written for R.L. Talley
    - [ca. 1950] (Box 1)
      Planning report, Consumer Advertising Program, Merck and Co., Inc., 1951-1953
    - 1960 July 29 (Box 1)
      Sales Manual
    - 1965 Dec. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1909-1967 and undated
    Contains correspondence between the Charles W. Hoyt Company and its business associates or clients. The majority of the correspondence with the Company is letters of congratulations or condolence, except for the letters between William Benton and Winthrop Hoyt.
    Includes letters pertaining to Charles W. Hoyt's resignation from Armour and Company and his founding of the Charles W. Hoyt Company in 1909; others are between Winthrop Hoyt and William Benton, one of the founders of the Benton and Bowles advertising agency. Their correspondence discusses the founding of Benton and Bowles and Winthrop Hoyt's proposal to Benton that he work for the Hoyt Company to assist in its reorganization. (See also the D'Arcy Masius Benton and Bowles Archives in the Hartman Center.)
    Correspondence relating to client accounts exists only for Merck and Co. (manufacturing chemists). Correspondence with the Charles B. Knox Co. predates Hoyt's acquisition of the account. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1909 (Box 1)
      Relating to Charles W. Hoyt's resignation from Armour and Company and founding of the Charles W. Hoyt Company
    - 1924-1929 (Box 1)
      Between William Benton and Winthrop Hoyt
    - 1924-1957 and undated (Box 1)
      Relating to Winthrop Hoyt's employment in England
    - 1928 (Box 1)
      Relating to the death of Charles W. Hoyt
    - 1928 (Box 1)
      Congratulating Winthrop Hoyt on his election as President of Charles W. Hoyt Company
    - 1929-1967 (Box 1)
      Between Charles W. Hoyt Company and Merck and Co.
    - 1934-1948 (Box 1)
      Relating to the acquisition of the Charles B. Knox Co. account
  - Financial Records, 1909-1963
    Records of financial conditions, client lists, and annual billings of the Charles W. Hoyt Company survive for most years of the company's existence. There are lists of income and expenses, billings listed by client, general conditions, and gross profits for the Hoyt Company. Also includes an expense book of trial balances and comparative statements from the first ten years of the company's existence. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1909-1919 (Box 1)
      Trial Balances and Comparative Statement, in a George B. Woolson Economy Expense Book
    - 1913-1963 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1924-1963 and undated
    Includes photographs of employees and company activities, most of which have been removed from scrapbooks for preservation purposes. See also Oversize Materials. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1924 July (Box 1)
      International Advertising Convention, London
    - 1941-1945 and undated (Box 1)
      Miscellaneous photographs
    - 1948 (Box 1)
      Gilbert commercial, CBS, from scrapbook, 1943-1963, (see Oversize Materials), page 39
    - 1951 (Box 1)
      Board of Directors, from scrapbook, 1943-1963, (see Oversize Materials), page 61
    - 1952 (Box 1)
      Christmas party, from scrapbook, 1943-1963, (see Oversize Materials), page 76
    - Undated (Box 1)
      Group photographs, from scrapbook, 1943-1963, (see Oversize Materials), pages 68, 83
  - Printed Materials, 1909-1960
    Consists of company publications, house advertisements, pamphlets, booklets, programs, commemorations of company anniversaries, clippings and other printed materials produced by the Charles W. Hoyt Company. See also the Oversize Materials. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1909-1928 (Box 1)
      Includes pamphlets, booklets, programs, commemorations and miscellaneous printed material. Materials from 1919 mention Sam Meek, who worked with the Charles W. Hoyt Company before joining the J. Walter Thompson Company advertising agency.
    - 1914 (Box 1)
      Publication: Newspaper Classified Advertising
    - 1917 (Box 1)
      Publication: The Preparation of a Marketing Plan, by Charles W. Hoyt
    - 1919-1930 (Box 1)
      House advertisements
    - 1919-1960 (Box 1)
      Clippings file consists of newspaper and magazine articles on Charles W. Hoyt and the Charles W. Hoyt Company, articles written by Charles W. Hoyt, and obituaries. See also Oversize Materials.
    - 1927 (Box 1)
      Publication: Planned Advertising: the Planned Approach to Agency Efficiency, by George French
    - 1939 (Box 1)
      30th Anniversary commemoration, Hoyt Chronicles, 1909-1939
    - 1943-1945 (Box 1)
      Newsletter, Hoyt-Poloi
    - 1944-1945 (Box 1)
      Travel and Recreation Survey, including an analysis of 1944 New England vacations
    - 1960 (Box 1)
      Publication, C.B. Donovan: 50 Years at Hoyt Agency
  - Scrapbooks, 1924-1963
    Contains scrapbooks compiled by the Hoyt Company which pertain to company anniversary celebrations, company activities and clients, as well as to the general state of advertising. Winthrop Hoyt's involvement and leadership with the American Association of Advertising Agencies is also documented in this subseries. The International Advertising Convention Scrapbook consists of printed material, programs, clippings, and other items from the convention, held in London in 1924. The scrapbook has been dismantled and foldered in its original chronological order. See the Photographs folders for photographs removed from the scrapbook. The 30th, 40th, and 50th Anniversary scrapbooks primarily consist of congratulatory correspondence, but also include a few clippings and printed materials. See also Oversize Materials. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1924 June-Oct., 5 folders (Box 1)
      International Advertising Convention, London, England
    - 1939 Apr. (Box 2)
      Charles W. Hoyt Company, Inc. 30th Anniversary Dinner
    - 1949 (Box 2)
      Charles W. Hoyt Company, Inc. 40th Anniversary
    - 1959 (Box 2)
      Charles W. Hoyt Company, Inc. 50th Anniversary
  - Writings on Advertising, 1913-1959
    Consists of writings by Charles, Winthrop, and Everett Hoyt relating to advertising. See also the Family Series for additional writings by Charles and Winthrop. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1913-1925 (Box 2)
      Charles W. Hoyt, several articles on planned advertising
    - 1924, 1941 (Box 2)
      Winthrop Hoyt, Observations on the British Market, 1924, and Flying the Great Circle, 1941
    - 1959 (Box 2)
      Everett Hoyt, New York Market: In the Whole or in Segments, It's [sic] Nation's Biggest Buy
- Family Series, 1894-1973 and undated (bulk 1908-1941)
  Consists of personal materials relating to Hoyt family members, including Charles W. Hoyt, Effie Smith Hoyt, Winthrop Hoyt, and Everett Red Hoyt. The series is divided into the following categories: the Charles B. Woolson Company and Family Financial Records, Correspondence, Diaries of Winthrop Hoyt and Effie Smith Hoyt, Newspapers, Visual Materials, and the Writings and Drawings of Charles W. and Winthrop Hoyt.
  - Charles B. Woolson Company and Family Financial Records, 1906-1961
    Includes ownership and activities of the George B. Woolson Company, a small mail order stationery business which Charles W. Hoyt operated from 1903-1928. A key product of the company was the Woolson Economy Expense Book. Also in this series are Charles and Winthrop's household and personal expense books, along with the investment records of Effie Smith Hoyt after the death of Charles W. Hoyt, including the value of his investments upon his death.
    See also Trial Balances and Comparative Statement book located in the Financial Records category of the Company Series. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1906-1909 (Box 2)
      Charles W. Hoyt, household and personal expense book
    - 1918-1928 (Box 2)
      George B. Woolson Co. correspondence
    - 1919-1926, 2 folders (Box 2)
      Winthrop Hoyt, personal expense books
    - 1928-1961 (Box 2)
      Effie Smith Hoyt, investment records
  - Correspondence, 1908-1973 and undated
    Consists of correspondence to members of the Hoyt family. It includes letters to Effie and Everett Hoyt from Winthrop while at Camp Winnepesaukee. See also Company Series for additional correspondence to members of the Hoyt family. Postcards were photocopied and originals transferred to the Postcard Collection. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1908-1916 (Box 2)
      Postcards; see also Visual Materials folders in this series
    - 1914 May 8 (Box 2)
      RSVPs for Winthrop Hoyt party at the New Haven Country Club
    - 1918 and undated (Box 2)
      Female friends to Winthrop Hoyt
    - 1918-1919 (Box 2)
      Winthrop Hoyt to Everett and Effie Smith Hoyt, Camp Winnepesaukee
    - 1918-1923 (Box 2)
      Relating to Winthrop Hoyt's student days at Yale College
    - 1932-1933 (Box 2)
      Winthrop and Everett Hoyt to Effie Smith Hoyt
    - 1963 Jan.-Feb. (Box 2)
      Condolences relating to the death of Effie Smith Hoyt
    - 1973 (Box 2)
      Get-well cards to Winthrop Hoyt
  - Diaries of Winthrop Hoyt and Effie Smith Hoyt, 1913 July 29-1919 Sept. 1
    Includes two diaries kept by Winthrop Hoyt as a teenager when he led hiking trips in the White Mountains (Mt. Chocorua and Mt. Washington) of New Hampshire for Camp Winnepesaukee. A third diary was written by Effie Smith Hoyt on a trip to England and France in the summer of 1913. She also compiled a postcard album of her trip which is located in the Scrapbooks folders.
    See also the Correspondence, Printed Materials, and the Visual Materials categories of the Family Series for materials related to Camp Winnepesaukee. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1913 July 29-Aug. 27 (Box 2)
      Effie Smith Hoyt, European trip
    - 1918 Aug. 12; 1919 Aug. 18-Sept. 1 (Box 2)
      Winthrop Hoyt, Camp Winnepesaukee hiking trips
  - Newspapers, 1918-1919 and undated
    Includes issues of newspapers, and a publication from Camp Winnepesaukee that describes the activities of the camp. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1918 July-Aug. (Box 2)
      The Reveille, the newspaper from Camp Winnepesaukee
    - 1919 (Box 2)
      Publication, Camp Winnepesaukee
    - Undated, Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Visual Materials, 1913, 1918-1919 and undated
    - Photographs, 1918-1919 and undated (Box 2)
      Consists of a photograph from Camp Winnepesaukee from 1918 or 1919, a photograph of Winthrop Hoyt as a child, and two photographs of unidentified boys.
    - Post Card Album, European Trip, 1913 (Box 2)
      Contains photocopies of a postcard album compiled by Effie Smith Hoyt on her trip to England and France in 1913. The album was dismantled and original postcards were transferred to the Postcard Collection.
  - Writings and Drawings of Charles W. and Winthrop Hoyt, 1894-1941
    Includes the writings of Charles W. and Winthrop Hoyt and material while students at Yale University. Also included are a short story from 1941 about airline travel and the details of a business trip to the West Coast. Correspondence showing Winthrop Hoyt's work on the Yale News and other family letters are located under the Family Series Correspondence category. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1894 (Box 2)
      Charles W. Hoyt, The Next Naval War
    - 1894 (Box 2)
      Charles W. Hoyt, Mechanical Refrigeration and the Practicality of Small Plants, Honors Thesis, Yale University
    - 1910-1914 (Box 2)
      Winthrop Hoyt, drawings, Worthington Hooker School
    - 1922 (Box 2)
      Winthrop Hoyt, The American Newspaper, and Political Influence of Horace Greeley as Editor of the New York Tribune, Yale University
    - 1941 (Box 2)
      Winthrop Hoyt short story, Flying the Great Circle
- Winthrop Hoyt World War II Series, 1942-1946 and undated
  Documents Hoyt's service during the war as an intelligence officer with the 7th Anti-Submarine Squadron, the 78th Bomb Squadron, the 45th Bomb Group, the 490th Bomb Group, and the 452nd Bomb Group. Hoyt was stationed in Jacksonville, Fla.; Boise, Ida.; Trinidad; and London. Contains correspondence, photographs, Nazi medals, song lyrics, writings, clippings, and printed material accumulated by Winthrop Hoyt while serving with the United States Army Air Force. Photographs are mostly aerial shots of submarines taken from Army Air Force planes. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Correspondence, Army Air Force, 1942 Mar. - 1946 May (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, clippings, tickets and receipts, 1943-1944 and undated (Box 2)
  - Observations, wartime reminiscences by Winthrop Hoyt, undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 1942-1944 and undated (Box 2)
  - Song lyrics, undated (Box 2)
    [ Rum and Coca Cola, Small Island, Come and Join the Air Corps, and The Flying Bigby Song]
- Oversize Materials
  - Company Series (Box 3)
    - Company Manuals: Sales Manual, revised, 1919-1927 (Box 3)
    - Scrapbooks
      - International Advertising convention, London, 1924 July (Box 3)
      - Charles W. Hoyt Company, Inc., 1943-1963
        - Use Copy, pages 1-136, 2 folders (Box 3)
        - Loose Items from Page 127, 1959 (Box 3)
  - Restricted and Closed Materials (Box 4)
    - Charles W. Hoyt Company Scrapbook, 1943-1963 (Box 4)
      Original CLOSED for preservation purposes. See Use Copy (photocopy) in Box 3
    - World War II: Two Nazi Medals, [ca. 1939] (Box 4)
      NOTE: FOR USE ONLY WITH STAFF SUPERVISION